Gemma HerbalCare is built for places where professional care may be far away, expensive, or delayed.
This is not a free-form herbal chatbot. It is a safety-first navigator: red flags are checked before any local plant is shown.
The app is local-first and Gemma-ready, so the same workflow can run with a local model such as Gemma through Ollama for private, low-connectivity settings.
The herb library keeps curated records: plant names, reference images, safety warnings, evidence level, interactions, and local availability.
This matters because the safest plant advice starts with correct identification and clear limits, not guessing.
The safety page draws the product boundary. The assistant is educational only, not a doctor, not a diagnosis, and not a prescription.
For severe symptoms, suspected malaria, breathing trouble, pregnancy bleeding, cancer cure claims, or chest pain, the system suppresses herbal substitution.
The consultation form collects context first: location, symptoms, age, duration, pregnancy status, care access, medicines, conditions, and allergies.
Care access changes the answer. If a clinic or community health worker is reachable, herbs are framed as reference only.
If care is not reachable right now, the app gives temporary harm-reduction guidance, but keeps warning that proven care is still the safest path.
Accessibility is part of the design. Camera and microphone support are marked as phase 2, for local OCR, voice input, and visual triage support.
The read-aloud button works now with browser text-to-speech, helping users who cannot read, cannot type, have poor vision, or are older adults.
Case one: child diarrhea after unsafe water. The lifesaving step is ORS and safe water. Herbs are supportive only, never the main treatment.
Case two: long-term food source planning. The app can suggest simple resilience steps such as sweet potato vines, familiar leafy foods, and chickens only when water, shade, and protection are realistic.
Case three: fever and suspected malaria. The app pushes rapid testing and proven antimalarial care. It does not recommend raw bark or herbs as a substitute.